A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6251, etc.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
1710: Deposit, June 21, 1943; Gift July 1, 1991 6111-r: Gift, July 28, 1959 6251: Deposit, March 19, 1960; Gift July 1, 1991 6251-a: Deposit, April 6, 1960 6251-b: Deposit, April 16, 1960 6251-c: Purchase, November 8, 1962 6251-d: Purchase, November 27-28, 1962 6251-e: Purchase, January 22, 1963 6251-f: Purchase, January 30, 1962 6251-g: Purchase, December 10, 1962 6251-h: Purchase, October 6, 1961 6251-i: Purchase, October 18, 1963 6251-j: Transferred to RBR on March 23, 1966 6251-k: Purchase, February 28, 1964 6251-l: Purchase, April 29, 1964 6251-m: Deposit, January 8, 1965; Gift July 1, 1991 6251-n: Purchase, February 12, 1965 6251-o: Purchase, April 6, 1965 6251-p: Purchase, May 13, 1965 6251-q: Purchase, November 26, 1965 6251-r: Purchase, February 15, 1966 6251-s: Purchase, March 21, 1966 6251-t: Purchase, January 10, 1968 6251-u: Archival transfer: January 11, 1968 6251-v: Purchase, March 14, 1968 6251-w: Purchase, May 17, 1968 6251-x: Purchase, May 30, 1968 6251-y: Purchase, May 31, 1968 6251-z: Purchase, May 9, 1969 6251-aa: Gift, February 22, 1970 6251-ab: Gift, February 22, 1970 6251-ac: Purchase, November 3, 1971 6251-ad: Gift, December 16, 1971 6251-ae: Gift, December 17, 1971 6251-af: Purchase, March 14, 1973 6251-ag: Deposit and Gift, April 19, 1973 6251-ah: Purchase, September 27, 1973 6251-ai: Gift, June 23, 1974 6251-aj: Deposit, October 28, 1974; Gift July 1, 1991 6251-ak: Deposit, November 26, 1975; Gift July 1, 1991 6251-al: Transfer from Rare Book Dept. 6251-am: Deposit, May 25, 1979; Gift July 1, 1991 6251-an: Transfer from Rare Book Dept: March 2, 1982 6251-ao: Purchase, July 28, 1983 6251-ap: Purchase, December 30, 1985 6251-aq: Purchase, December 17, 1987 6251-ar: Purchase, April 2, 1992 6251-as: Purchase, February 11, 1993 6251-at: Purchase, January 20, 1994 6251-au: Purchase, n.d. 6251-av: Purchase, March 29, 1994 6251-aw: Purchase, June 15, 1994 6251-ax: Purchase, October 25, 1994 6251-ay: Purchase, January 5, 1995 6251-az: Purchase, May 18, 1995 6251-ba: Purchase, November 18, 1995 6251-bb: Purchase, February 13, 1996 6251-bc: Purchase, July 18, 1996 6251-bd: Purchase, November 1, 1996 6251-be: Purchase, December 23, 1996 6251-bf: Purchase, January 7, 1998 6251-bg: Purchase, December 17, 1998 6251-bh: Purchase, March 30, 1999 6251-bi: Archival Transfer, September 14, 1999 6251-bj: Gift, July 23 1975 6251-bk: Purchase, February 22, 1980 6251-bl: Purchase, May 16, 2001 6251-bm: Purchase, August 29, 2001 6251-bn: Purchase, January 29, 2002 9511-q: Purchase, January 16, 1980 10430: Gift, December 12, 1980
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry James was born on April 15, 1843 in New York City into a wealthy family. His father, Henry James Sr. was one of the best-known intellectuals in mid-nineteenth-century America. In his youth James traveled back and forth between Europe and America. He studied with tutors in Geneva, London, Paris, Bologna and Bonn. At the age of 19 he briefly attended Harvard Law School, but preferred reading literature to studying law. James published his first short story, A Tragedy of Errors two years later, and devoted himself to literature. In 1866-1869 and 1871-1872 he was a contributor to the Nation and Atlantic Monthly.
From an early age James read the classics of English, American, French and German literature and Russian classics in translation. His first novel, Watch And Ward (1871), was written while he was traveling through Venice and Paris. After living in Paris, where he was contributor to the New York Tribune, James moved to England, living first in London and then in Rye, Sussex. During his first years in Europe James wrote novels that portrayed Americans living abroad. In 1905 James visited America for the first time in twenty-five years, and wrote Jolly Corner.
Among James' masterpieces are Daisy Miller (1879), The Portrait Of A Lady (1881), The Bostonians (1886), What Maisie Knew (1897), and The Wings Of The Dove (1902). James considered The Ambassadors (1903) his most 'perfect' work of art. James's most famous short story is The Turn of the Screw, a ghost story in which the question of childhood corruption obsesses a governess. Although James is best known for his novels, his essays are now attracting a more general audience.
Between 1906 and 1910 James revised many of his tales and novels for the New York edition of his complete works. His autobiography, A Small Boy And Others, appeared in 1913 and was continued in Notes Of A Son And Brother (1914). The third volume, The Middle Years, appeared posthumously in 1917. The outbreak of World War I was a shock for James and in 1915 he became a British citizen as a declaration of loyalty to his adopted country and in protest against the United States' refusal to enter the war. James suffered a stroke on December 2, 1915. He died three months later in Rye on February 28, 1916.
Scope and Content
Consists of ca. 775 items, including manuscripts, galley proofs, correspondence, and photographs. Manuscripts include three chapters from The Europeans; the last page from Glasses; the typed manuscript of Honoré Daumier; James's reviews of Emile Zola's book, Nana, and Elizabeth Stoddard's book, Two Men; corrections to the printed edition of Princess Casamassima; James's play Saloon; and the original of Daudet's Tourgeneff with James's original translation.
Also included are galley proofs and drafts of works about Henry James and his writings, such as Henry James at Home by Montgomery Hyde; Lady Barberina and Other Tales edited by Herbert Ruhm; The Master by Ford Madox Ford; and a poem dedicated to Henry James from Max Beerbohm and Edmund Gosse entitled To Henry James.
In his extensive correspondence, James discusses his travels, the nature of his writings, his social appointments, and his ailments. Of special interest is his relationship with Violet Hunt, who was the long time mistress of Ford Madox Ford. Henry James took great interest in Violet Hunt, and his letters to her are very flirtatious and intriguing. James's relationship with Violet Hunt temporarily ended when the scandal erupted over Ford Madox Ford's wife not granting a divorce to Ford while he remained involved with Hunt. In a letter dated November 2, 1909, James makes the difficult choice not to continue his relationship with Hunt until Ford's divorce is finalized.
Henry James's correspondence with his close friend Hendrick Christian Anderson, an American sculptor, is extensive. James shows great admiration and love and interest in Anderson's work as well as lengthy criticism of it. James worries over Anderson's health, his attack of vertigo, and whether he is working too hard. James admires his youth, courage, and genius, and envies him his studio in Rome, even though his heart "bleeds" at the vision of him alone in that "wicked and indifferent" city.
Also of interest are James's letters to Mrs. Humphrey Ward. Most of his letters express critical acclaim for her works, although occasionally he gives negative criticism. He tells her that she is the only British romancer he can read. In one long letter, James defends his method of writing fiction and discusses at great length the art of writing in general with examples from his various books.
Other correspondents Douglas Ainslie, H. B. Brewster, Donald Brien, Grace Carter, Theodore Child, Sir John Clark, Alvin Langdon Coburn, Joseph Conrad, Francis Marion Crawford, Daniel Sargent Curtis, Leon Edel, Clare Frewen, Morton Fullerton, Edmund Gosse, Mrs. [Alice Stopfard] Green, Hattie E. Hathaway, Julian Hawthorne, Mrs. Henschel, H. Montgomery Hyde, Alice James, Henry James, Sr., Henry James III, William James (brother of Henry James), William James, Jr. (nephew of Henry James), Robert Underwood Johnson, Edna Kenton, Ford M. Ford, Katherine P. Loring, Lena Milman, James Osgood, LeRoy Phillips, Allan Wade, and Hugh Walpole.
Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Documents include an article about the poor reception of Henry James's play, Guy Domville, at the St. James Theatre; an interview with Alvin L. Coburn about Henry James; the Introductory Address for H. Montgomery Hyde by Cliffton Waller Barrett; various notes about Henry James, Sr.; and photocopies of the book jackets for The Outcry and The Finer Grain.
Finally, Photographs and Portraits contain numerous images of Henry James and his residence at Lamb House, Rye, England. Also included are images of Henry James, Sr.; cartoons of Henry James by Max Beerbohm; an image of Dr. Baldwin, a friend of Henry James who was an American expatriate living in Italy; and miscellaneous photographs of persons and places associated with Henry James.
Arrangement
The Papers of Henry James is arranged in four series. Series I: Literary Manuscripts is arranged alphabetically by title. Series II, Correspondence, is arranged in three subseries. Subseries A: Dated correspondence of Henry James, is arranged chronologically. Subseries B: Undated Henry James correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by recipient. Subseries C: Other correspondents, is arranged chronologically by correspondent. Series III: Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Documents and Series IV: Photographs and Portraits, are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
  - The Europeans by Henry James n.d., AMsS (Box-folder 1:1)
    Autograph manuscript for chapters, VII, VIII, and IX. #6251-a
  - Glasses by Henry James, [1914?], TMsS 1 p. on 1 l.; with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Last page of typed manuscript beginning: "You haven't quarreled with her, I hope." #6251-b
  - Henry James at Home by Montgomery Hyde [ca. 1969], TMs. (Box-folder 1:3)
    #6251-ab
  - Henry James at Home by Montgomery Hyde [ca. 1969], TMs. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Honoré Daumier by Henry James n.d., TMsS, 23 pp. on 23 l. (Box-folder 1:5)
    #6251-f
  - Lady Barberina and Other Tales by Henry James [ca. 1961], Corrected galley proofs by Herbert Ruhm. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Notes and Introduction by Herbert Ruhm. #6251-ae
  - Lady Barberina and Other Tales by Henry James [ca. 1961], corrected galley proofs by Herbert Ruhm. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Lady Barberina and Other Tales by Henry James [ca. 1961] (Box-folder 1:8)
    Corrected galley proofs by Herbert Ruhm. #6251-ae
  - The Master by Ford Madox Ford"> n.d., TMs, 23 pp. on 23 l.; with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Written for The American Mercury. #6251-a
  - Nana by Henry James [ca. 1880], AMsS, 16 pp. on 16 l. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Review of Emil Zola's book, Nana. #6251-l
  - A Passionate Pilgrim by Henry James n.d., Negative Photostats, 5 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Autograph corrections to printed edition. Location of originals unknown. #6251-am
  - The Princess Casamassima by Henry James n.d., 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Autograph corrections to 1887 one volume edition. These corrections made by James appear in later editions of the novel. #6251-x
  - The Saloon: A Play in One Act by Henry James 1928, TMs, 72 pp. on 72 l. (Box-folder 1:13)
    #6251-be
  - To Henry James by MB [Max Beerbohm] and EG [Edmund Gosse] 1908 September 6, AMs, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:14)
    #6251-a
  - Tourgeneff by Alphonse Daudet with English translation by Henry James, n.d., AMss, 33 pp. on 33 l. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Translation missing page 13. #6251-b
  - Tourgeneff by Alphonse Daudet with English translation by Henry James, 2005, facsimile, 1 volume. (Box-folder 1:16)
    #6251-b
  - Two Men: A Novel by Elizabeth Stoddard by Henry James 1865, AMs, 23 pp. on 23 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Review of Two Men. #6251-f
    - Henry James to W[endell] P[hillips] Garrison, [1872?] December 14, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:18)
      James, Paris, encloses a review [not present] of George Eliot's Middlemarch for publishing in The Nation and discusses various pieces for publication, including writings on the Parisian stage, Henri Regnault, Auguste Laugel, and a journey in Italy. #6251-ba
    - [Henry James] to Mr. Osgood, [1876] March 7, ANS, 1 p. on 1 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 1:19)
      Here is another batch of The American copy. There are 30 pages more of the Atlantic to send him, which shall go as soon as possible. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [F. R.] Osgood, [1877] February 13, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. mounted. (Box-folder 1:20)
      Sending herewith all the rest of copy for The American that James has the material for two packets. The last he will have as soon as he receives it. He said he did not expect to see proof himself, but should extremely like to have it sent to his father for final revision. With all hopes for the book's prosperity. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mr. Nelson, 1878 December 9, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:21)
      Sends Mr. Nelson the last chapter but one: XXXVII of James's serial. #6251-m
    - H[enry] James to Mrs. Hertz, [ca. 1879-1880] March 4, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:22)
      Kind of her to find time to write him regarding Major MacDonnell's death, and her inability to receive on Sunday. Sorry it causes her any regrets. Shall come soon and pay his deferred visit. MacDonnell's death is being very kindly noticed. Regards to Mr. Hertz and her daughter. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to Mrs. Hertz, [1879] March 17, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:23)
      Didn't answer note of the 13th as expected to make reply in person by promising self in Harley Street, but at last minute was prevented. Shall come next Sunday. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to Mr. Huntington, [1879?] April 23, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:24)
      Has taken a liberty and hastens to confess it. He has given an introduction to him to an Englishman who has gone to stay in Paris: T. G. Child. He is a young journalist (Pall Mall Gazette, etc.) and though a bit of a Bohemian, and furthermore a Jew, but doesn't feel he is outraging the sanctity of his private life. He is modest, honest, ingenious and excellent. He knows no one in Paris where he has gone to work. Hopes he can let him come and gossip once in a while. Confident of his benevolence. Hopes he has returned. Believes he is philosophic. For himself he is cockneyfied "to a degree," quite naturalized in London. Suits him better than Paris, but hopes to visit the latter with the advent of summer. #6251-c
    - H[enry] James to [Theodore] Child, [1879] December 15, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:25)
      Bolted from Paris too abruptly to say good-bye. Shall be passing through before long and they can make it up. Back in London, and as cocknefied as if he had never been away. Please send him 4 or 5 numbers of the [Cenos Parisian ?] if there is any notice of his piece. Also send him Nana so he may do it. #6251-c
    - H[enry] James to "My dear Sir" [Mr. Hertz], [1879-1880] December 29, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:26)
      Happy to dine with him January 12. Excuse his delay in answering his note, which had to be forwarded. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to John G. Barron, 1880 January 19, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:27)
      Received his letter of January 5. Has no prospect of being able to contribute anything more to the N.A.R. [North American Review ?]. Engaged in work which leaves him no time for writing "articles." If he can do anything, will let him hear of it. Afraid a comparison between English and American manners would be too invidious and ticklish a theme, especially while he continues to reside in England. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to [Theodore] Child, 1880 February 4, ALS, 8 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:28)
      Thanks for note that gratifies and alarms him. Began to hear of vogue of Bundle of Letters in United States, and was glad as assumed demand was being supplied by Parisian with proportionate profit. Heard from father that piratical Loring of Boston was about to bring out pamphlet edition of it. Wrote Harper's to sell them the American copyright so they may bring out sole authorized edition. Has not posted to Parisian the permanent property of the thing. Same proceeding with Daisy Miller and The International Episode which originally appeared in Cornhill. There was an attempt to pirate them in the United States so he immediately sold copyright to Harper's, who brought them out in little pamphlets which had a great circulation. As Child says he has authorized American edition, afraid he is under impression that James did not reserve the copyright. James understood he was not to publish simultaneously in American periodical, but not in the least that he was not subsequently to republish it. As long as it could be sold simply in Parisian form, he was not happy to stay his hand. Seems he should get what he can for it as a book, even though only 50 pages in paper cover. Loring has committed legal misdemeanor in republishing it as a book without James's consent, anything published by James anywhere. If Harper's accepts his offer, they will proceed against him. Complicates matter that Child's pamphlet should appear. Write and tell him if Child's agent has gone to work before he can be stopped. Thanks for his news. Shall probably be in Paris around March 1. #6251-c
    - H[enry] James to [Theodore] Child, [1880] February 6, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:29)
      Understands situation. His ultimate property in story would enable him to protect himself legally in America. Assumed Child knew about copyrights there, which would for the moment ensure the sale of the Parisian. James's belief is that as American owner of copyright, he could prosecute for any complete republication, even in a newspaper. James should have inserted at top of the Bundle a notification that American copyright was reserved by the author. If Harper's accepts his offer they may be trusted to supplant everyone else. #6251-c
    - Henry James to Joseph [Hatton], 1880 February 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:30)
      Greatly obliged to [New York Times] and to him, but he is immersed in engagements to write what will occupy him for next twelve months. Work on hand and in prospect makes it impossible for him to undertake anything else. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to [Theodore] Child, [1880] February 17, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:31)
      Here is notice of Nana which is longer than he meant it to be. Print it as soon as he can with only three conditions: 1. send him two copy proofs, 2. print it in leaded, 3. send him one-half dozen copies of papers. Will send proofs to American paper in advance to take revenge on all others who would steal from the Parisian. How unnaturally filthy is the book! #6251-c
    - H[enry] James to [Theodore] Child, [1880] April 6, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:32)
      Thanks for notes regarding novel. Glad it gave him pleasure. Shall do something, yet much better. Shall write publisher to send book to him. It is being well noticed in London. Doesn't it seem pitiful in Paris that the old Vicar of Wakefield, drearily vulgarized, is only a dramatic novelty now? Has moments of Paris reminiscence so acute that he can hardly break off there. Shall not to there before the summer. #6251-c
    - Henry James to Mrs. Hertz, [1880] April 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:33)
      Returning from Naples, finds her note offering him a pleasure which he is sorry to have missed. Hopes she lost no time in seeking a substitute for office she invited him to fill. Should have been happy to meet distinguished foreigners. Has been abroad since March 1, and is enjoying that peace of mind which Italy alone can give. Excited by the constant bulletins about liberal victories, the magnitude of which quite exceed his dreams. Hopes the party will make a better figure in office than it has lately made in opposition! Finds Italy more Italy than ever, almost a compensation for loss of London hospitalities. Hopes to return in a few weeks to make the acquaintance of her new home, and her daughter. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to [Robert] Thomson, [1880] December 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:34)
      Sorry he shall not have the pleasure of seeing him next week. Leaves town the 23rd to spend Christmas in the country, and will not return until the early part of January. Regrets missing his visit. Expects to start for the continent for an absence of several months, spending winter and spring in Rome. But London is his permanent headquarters, and he constantly returns, so sooner or later they shall meet. Sent his letter to his brothers who will be glad for news of him. #6251-m
    - H[enry] James to Sir John [Clark], [1881] March 16, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:35)
      Sitting looking down on picturesque port of Genoa. It is Italy! Local color in which the nose is as conscious as the eyes. It smells picturesque! Has been staying at San Remo, after a fortnight in Paris. San Remo is a lovely coast: a supportable form of modified martyrdom, which he feels as he grows older modern travel to be. San Remo more charming even than Provence: a sort of Italian Falmouth. Hope he is happy and healthy, and enjoying Cornish spring, which much be flowery enough. Even in Falmouth he must have jumped at the sound of the horrible Russian bombs. Isn't he glad he is not an Emperor? The thing is too devilish, and he doesn't believe in reforms that begin in deforming. Exempt from Ireland the last two weeks. They know nothing of it in Genoa, and he reads the Times in a hazy, dreamy manner. Will go to Venice, then Rome. #6251-n
    - H[enry] James to Sir John [Clark], [1882] January 8, ALS, 10 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:36)
      Meant to send him a greeting, but America isn't a land of leisure, but it is to a certain extent that of pleasure. Wants to give him a few of his novels, and asks for as many as possible of his own. If he were to relate his adventures and impressions, he wouldn't know where to begin. His adventures chiefly impressions, as he has not been traveling extensively. Spent a month in Boston and on in New York. Rest of time in Washington, D. C., the most interesting of the three. Found friends the Adams's, whose agreeable house is one of the features of Washington. They like Washington better than London because they are, vulgarly speaking, someone here, and are nothing in his complicated kingdom. He and Lady Clark the first Europeans they asked about. Everyone genial and friendly in D.C., and he, too, is "someone" there, and it will be a sacrifice of vanity when he returns to England. But he loves his London better than his vanity and will turn up there in May. Things are fast in D.C., and change in the last ten years incredible. Increase of civilization, wealth, knowledge, taste, etc. is striking. Won't answer for what the county may become in 100 years hence. New York is a brilliant city, but it takes a fortune to enjoy it. Nothing under a million is called a great fortune now. Believes Washington is place in the world where money or its absence matters least. It is informal, familiar, essentially social and conversational, enormously big and yet extremely provincial, indefinably ridiculous yet agreeable. Only place in America where there is no business, where an air of leisure hangs over the streets, where one walks slowly and doesn't look preoccupied. Hasn't seen his minister, Sackville-West, but he appears much liked, and he has a most attractive daughter. Where is he? Hasn't forgotten his scheme to sail to the Cape. Is he rubbing shoulders with the Kaffirs and tossing on a Southern ocean? James is homesick for the chimney pots of London. His sojourn in D.C. is an exile mitigated by optimism. Tell him of Boers and Kaffirs. #6251-n